Hello and welcome back to another video
it, ItsDrdan, and today we're gonna be
learning about heating and cooling curve.
Now, what these are used for is
that in thermochemistry we like
to illustrate how things, uh,
or substances absorb or release.
So this is typically showing how phase
changes occur and how essentially
being absorbed or released.
So what does this kind of look like?
Well, the heating curves and cooling
curves can be shown in a number of ways.
So the first one is essentially
if I have something that's
heating, these are usually shown
as a sloped line going upwards.
So heating, as you can see here,
uh, as temperature is changing.
So as it's going up.
So you can kind of imagine
like if I have a really low TI,
it's going to a very high Tf.
So when we are using these heating
curves, we'll usually use our M-cat
equation to illustrate that change as
it's going from one location to another.
The slopes use the M-cat equation.
Now, same thing for cooling.
Cooling is the exact same idea, right?
We're gonna have a slope, but instead
it's gonna go the opposite way, right?
It's going downward as a result.
So whenever we have a downward slope,
generally the Q value turns out to be.
Negative mathematically.
Um, the reason is, is because
your TI is gonna be a lot greater
than the F, so essentially you'll
get a negative value from this
versus the other one from before.
Um, TF is greater than the I.
It's all depending on kind of what you're
seeing value and where you're starting.
Right.
Now when you have a phase change to
represent this well, if you can kind of
remember the equations for those, usually
we use, uh, Q is equal to N times delta
H of either the fusion or vaporization.
So one or the other.
So there is no delta T value or
temperature in that calculation at all.
So if you kind of think of this plot,
well, it's only temperature and energy.
So if temperature's not changing.
Should you plot it?
Well, in this case, what we
would end up doing is we would
show a plateau or a flat line.
So plateau versus a slope
for the other value.
Okay.
So slopes for the cooling and heating
curves and a plateau for phase change.
So phase changes can be like
boiling, they can be freezing,
they can be, um, condensation.
They can.
Um, evaporation.
It just depends on like what exactly
is that you're looking at with,
put it all together.
Essentially.
If I were to try to show like a
heating curve from like ice to steam,
it can look a little bit like this.
So notice how have many different slopes,
many different plateaus that are here.
So to kind of like label
them as different regions.
So let's just call 'em like A, B, C,
D, and E, Just kind of labeling them
by their, their slopes and plateaus.
So remember that whenever we see these
slopes represent heating, so it's going
up, changing plateaus or phase changes.
So whenever we have, let's
say, any of those slopes.
That's when we'll use a
Q as equal to MC delta D.
And then plateaus are using one of
the different phase change formulas,
whether it's Q is equal to N times delta
diffusion or N times delta vaporization.
So whenever we're seeing these, right,
all of these will have their own different
energy value associated with them.
So if I'm kind of looking at the
first one, which is A, right?
It's a rise in temperature, and
that's where you essentially have
ice, is absorbing its energy up here.
So at the very top.
So that what that's gonna tell
us is essentially that ice value
is gonna have its own unique C
value for ice, because ice is.
So what we'll use is that
Q equals MCAT, the B area.
So this would be like Q is one B, which is
Q2 or second heat is gonna be essentially
how it's gonna change and phase.
So you can see it's a, it takes a
long time for all those bonds to
kind of finally break apart going
from ice to a full on liquid.
If you kind of ever thrown, let's say
an ice cube water, you know how it
takes like a really long time usually
for it to melt if they're about the.
Well, that's because all those
molecules, they're stuck together.
They're really, really cold.
They don't have a lot of energy to
do that, so it's difficult for them
to try to release from one another.
Um, essentially then when we have have
three, we can see that this is Q3 area and
Q4 and so on, and every part represents
a different story of how we can read
it and see what the data is showing.
Okay.
Q4 and Q five.
Now why do we care about
all these different heats?
Well, if we were trying to solve,
let's say, a problem like this one,
and we needed to figure out, well,
what, how much heat does it take
to go from one spot to the other?
Well, this is when essentially to
do the total energy, you'd have to
add up all these individual parts.
We'd have to take Q1, add it to Q2.
Add it to Q3 and so on as you're
kind of going through all these
problems, which can be a really
long, hard, difficult problem.
Um, as you're trying to really see like,
okay, what is it that I'm trying to solve?
So this is what we're actually going
to be doing at the end of this, at the
end of the video is seeing this, but
before we do that, we're gonna actually
illustrate what these phase changes
look like on the molecular picture.
So I have an example to show you.
Yeah, up right up here.
All right, so in this tutorial, I
grabbed this from essentially a free
simulation software from the University
of Colorado, which goes through
many different types of examples.
So right here we have
neon, so a noble gas.
And when it's really, really cold,
it actually can become a solid.
Now when it's a noble gas,
these things don't take a lot
of heat from the break apart.
So what I'm gonna do here is I'm
gonna raise the heat so you can
see the little fire coming apart.
And what you notice is that the
molecules are moving around more.
So when we do that right, we're
increasing kinetic energy as a result.
So you can see it went from
14 to 22 Kelvin, not a big
change, but there's more energy.
And when that happens, you can kind of
see like, oh, these guys are starting
to break apart as a result, right?
So it's starting to kind of
transition to more of like a liquid.
As a result, it's kind of melting if
we raise it a little bit more, right?
So not much, but what we're gonna actually
see is it's gonna all start falling apart.
This is what we refer to as it's becoming
a, going from a solid to a liquid.
You notice how it was one big
cube and now it's kind of being
spread throughout all the bottom.
And being that we're still not
quite at the place where gases
are only gases, you can see where
things are actually vaporizing.
So kind of like how, uh, when you,
it's like the morning dew in the
morning when it's con condensed
all over like grass and leaves.
But over the day, as it heats up
it, it starts to just disappear.
Well, that's vaporization, right?
It's not getting to a boiling pot.
But when it gets enough energy that it
can actually break into a gas, it's all
about how fast are these guys moving?
If I kind of increase the temperature
by like maybe another 10, 20 degrees,
you can see, okay, now they're
all gas particles moving around
freely, Bouncing all over they one.
And you can kind of notice that there's
still some liquid here at the bottom for
a little while until I start increasing.
It takes a lot of energy to make
that phase change fully happen.
So that's the plateau in the slopes.
Let's take a look at a different molecule.
Okay, so this is solid water.
This is what a water molecule looks like
when it is in its, uh, when it's an ice.
So you can see everything is what we
refer to as hydrogen bonded together,
which is something that we're gonna talk
about in a few in a soon, in other videos.
Now, when in this phase, this is when
ice cubes, like they still move and
vibrate when they're in this phase.
It's at a hundred forty-six
Kelvin, or negative a hundred
and twenty-seven degrees C.
So the freezing point is at zero,
so you can still see it's a, it's
an ice cube, so they're still
moving at the molecular level.
So if I heat this up pretty
slowly, you can still see the
ice cube starts to expand.
It's still heating up.
So this is where the slope is, right?
We're going in that
heating curve direction.
Now as I get closer and
closer to zero degrees.
Notice how it's starting
to spread apart, right?
They're still really close together,
but now it's kind of starting to
look more like a liquid, right?
Things are starting to move and
try to travel over each other as a
result, and if I heated up a little
bit more, the molecules are gonna
start sliding across each other and
moving and really aren't that much of
a solid anymore, and it takes a lot
of effort and work for that to happen.
Now I heat that up to about,
let's say body temperature.
So right where kind of our bodies
are is about maybe 35, 36, 3, 7.
You'll be able to see, probably
some molecules might go into the
gas phase or get knocked off, but
most of it's still liquid, right?
So inside of you.
Right?
So that's why we, our water-based life
forms, if we went any higher and we
lost our water, that'd be really bad.
But if it gets too hot, let's
say around a hundred degrees c.
Right where the boiling point is.
Right here, you'll see, okay, this
is where steam starts coming from,
but we still have our liquid.
And if I go a little bit beyond that,
you'll see this is where Steam will
start kind of coming up and we'll
have our molecules be really excited
and turn into little gas particles.
Okay, we have steam that's
kind of going place.
I just wanna kind of show you
guys what slopes and that toes
kind of look like on a molecular.
Let's take a look at our final
example for, for these videos.
All right.
Our one example for this video is how
much total energy is required to heat one
kilogram of ice at negative 50 degrees
C to steam at 130 degrees Celsius.
The specific heats are for ice
li and for liquid water and
steam are all listed below.
And we also have the enthalpy for
both fusion and vaporization listed.
These are gonna be all your
Q values that you have here.
So one thing I mentioned before is
that the total Q value is all of
the different formulas, essentially
all added up and listed together.
So let's try to go through this
as quickly as we can to show this.
So how would we do it?
Well, being that we have a Q value, right?
And it's all, the first one is a slope.
So one kilogram of water is being heated.
So, being that we have, um,
one thing earlier is this is
the same slope from before.
Um, so with that being said, right, if
we want to do our blue portion, we're
going from negative 50 to zero degree.
So our final is zero,
negative 50 is our first part.
So what we will do is we'll times
that by the specific heat of ice.
Which in this case I have it in
kilojoules per kilogram to save
on us doing some conversions.
And that's gonna be essentially
zero minus negative 50 degrees.
And what that's going to become
for your Q1 is you're gonna have
one times 2.0, three times 50.
So we're gonna get 101.
Five kilojoules of heat
for the first slope, right?
So using that MCAT equation
for Q2, this is a plateau.
So this is when the water foils.
So being, once again, we are looking at,
uh, using our, uh, kilogram of liquid.
So we have one kilogram
that is being used here.
So when we are trying to use this, we can
quickly convert it to grams for ourselves
because we have to use the molar mass.
So 1000 grams, we're gonna times
that by the molar mass, which is
18 grams over one mole for water.
Um, and then we are going to,
um, to convert that as well using
the enthalpy of fusion, which is
6.00 kilojoules for every mole.
All right.
Now when we do that, what we are
going to get is 333.3 kilojoules.
That's a lot of energy for Q2.
Notice how much more energy
it took to do a phase change
instead of just heating ice up.
There's a big difference trying to
get over that hump and for it to
finally become what it needs to.
So let's kind of keep track
of all this for ourselves.
So we're gonna have 101.5 kilojoules,
and we're gonna add that plus
330 Three-point-three kilojoules.
Okay, the next part, so Q3 is heating up.
Again, this is going
from zero to 100 degrees.
So when we are doing that, once again,
we have our one kilogram to 1.00.
Kilograms.
We're gonna times that by
C of water, which is 4.184.
So where are we looking for that value?
That's coming from right here, right?
So we're on the liquid
portion of the slope.
This will show that, right?
We did the plateau.
Now we're going from here to here.
So it's at a hundred to zero.
All right?
So when we have that, so one kilogram.
Times 4.184, and this is in
kilojoules over grams, uh, kilograms
by Celsius times a hundred degrees.
C is our change in this case.
Now, when we do one times 100 times 4.184,
we're gonna get 418 kilojoules for Q3.
Okay?
We're gonna add that in
here to 418 kilojoules.
Change all that.
The pink to match.
Now for the purple part, which is our
next plateau, or the vaporization,
which as you can see here, look how much
energy this requires for this to happen.
To turn something into
a gas requires the most.
It's kind of like when a
liquid wants to be a gas.
It's kind of like ripping you
away from all your friends.
Like you want to hang out with
them, you don't wanna leave.
Well, it's kind of the same idea here.
So we have our 1000 grams of our Liquid.
We're going to turn that once again
into moles, just like we did before.
And then we're going to convert
that using our heat of vaporization,
which is 40.7 kilojoules per mole.
Okay.
Now when we do that, what we're going
to get is 2,260 joules of energy
for that portion of the equation,
which is the most out of any of them.
And then for our last part, which
is once again, another slope, we're
gonna take that one kilojoule times
up by the specific heat of steam,
just two kilojoules per kilogram.
Celsius and being that we're going
from one 30 to 100 or 100 to one 30,
sorry, this is gonna be a difference
of 30 degrees C, which is going to
equal 60.0 kilojoules of energy.
And what we are going to do
is we're gonna add up all of
these little pieces together.
So, and that's gonna make
our total energy as a result.
We're gonna take 101.5 plus 333.3 plus
four 18 plus 2 22 60 plus 60 kilojoules.
And once we do all that, we're
gonna get a massive value of
3172.1 kilojoules of energy.
That's a lot.
That's a lot of energy.
To kind of put that in perspective,
if you wanted to have that in joules.
That would be about, um, 170.
So let's say if we were to round that
to the proper sig figs, that would
be 10 to the six power of Joules.
So that is a lot.
Um, now I always get asked this
question like, is this kind of thing
on an exam usually not this long?
Like maybe a part of
it would be reasonable.
So like if you had to do just one of the
energy calculations, maybe one of the
parts, how to read the slopes, how to
read the plateaus, what do they show?
Just pieces.
Maybe adding two parts together,
like how we did in the heat of
fusion heat of vaporization video.
This one is a very long problem
that's typically done as maybe a
homework problem for like one homework
problem where it might take you a
while to do it, but it's practicing
all your pieces adding together.
I hope this video helped, and
thank you so much for listening,
and I'll all later, bye now.